A Guide to the Lyman Creighton Craig papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA134
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Manuscript materials, 1948-1976; 5
  - Publications not listed in Craig bibliography: Mss
    - L.C. Craig and J. Sogn "Isolation of antibiotics by countercurrent distribution", 1975 (Box 32, Folder 10)
      Correspondence; photocopy of published paper and working copy.
    - [NPI] L.C. Craig (Book review) Davis, E.J., Sterling, A.M. and Stewart, G.H., The determination of distribution coefficients in quaternary systems (Box 32, Folder 11)
      [Indications are this book reviewed for Industrial and engineering chemistry but no other information available].
      Typescript of review.
    - [NPI] R. Bockman, R. Gupta, W. Gibbons and L.C. Craig "The measurements of the amide proton exchange rates in the ring portion of the peptide antibiotic polymyxin B1 by the method of partially relaxed fast Fourier transform NMR spectroscopy and tritium-hydrogen exchange" (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - [NPI] R.S. Bockman, W.A. Gibbons and L.C. Craig "Amide proton exchange rates in a seven amino acid fragment of the antibiotic polymyxin B1 by the method of partially relaxed fast Fourier transform NMR spectroscopy and tritium-hydrogen exchange" (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - [NPI] R.E. Galardy, R.S. Bockman and L.C. Craig "Enzymatic cleavage of the polymyxin B ring" (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - [Unidentified] L.C. Craig "On the behavior of associating solutes in thin film dialysis experiments", Typescript with corrections (Box 32, Folder 15)
- Conferences, meetings, seminars, 1952-1973; 6
  See also under: National Academy of Sciences (for NAS meetings attended) in box no. 9 and also information on other meetings with published manuscript material.
  (some not identified) and Gordon Research Conferences 1952-1973.
  Consists of correspondence; programs; memorabilia; mss with working material; abstracts; outline; in some instances information sketchy and inconclusive
  - Meetings not identified: A group of presentations for meetings or student lecture notes, 3 folders (Box 33)
    Slide, graph material included.
    - "Film dialysis" (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Bacitracin A - L.C. Craig remarks (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - GSH experiments (group seminar) E. Stoner (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Baltimore, Md. Johns Hopkins University Charles E. Dohme memorial lectureship, 1952 February (Box 33, Folder 4)
    Papers delivered:.
    1) "The development of fractionation techniques for biochemical studies".
    2) "The use of countercurrent distribution in the study of polypeptides and proteins" Correspondence.
  - Stamford, Conn. American Cyanamid Co. Chemotherapy division lecture, 1953 January 15 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    Paper delivered "Some experiments with large molecular weight peptides".
  - NY City New York Section of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine symposium on diabetes mellitus, 1953 March 25 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    Paper delivered "Structure of insulin".
    Correspondence and program.
  - Bound Brook, N.J. Calco Div. American Cyanamid Co. lecture Title?, 1953 April 16 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Indianapolis, Ind. 7th Insulin conference. L.C. Craig to D. Stetten indicates report presented "The amino acid composition of a number of different insulins" (possible title) and possible report as supplement to insulin data on "The isolation of peptides from partial hydrolysates", 1953 May (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Baton Rouge, La. Louisiana State University symposium on modern methods of analytical chemistry Craig delivers 3 lectures on "extraction procedures", 1954 February 1-4 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    Correspondence includes other speakers and topics.
  - American Chemical Society Lectures, 1954 (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - ACS lecture tour #72: ACS local sections at, 1954 March
    - Columbus, Ohio, 1954 March 15
    - Wooster, Ohio, 1954 March 16
    - Painesville, Ohio, 1954 March 17
    - Erie, Pa, 1954 March 18
    - New Castle, Pa, 1954 March 19
      Paper delivered "Isolation and characterization of substance by extraction".
    - ACS Delaware section lecture at Wilmington, 1954 October 26
      Paper delivered "The analytical aspects of countercurrent distribution".
    - ACS Lecture tour #22 ACS local sections at, 1954 November
    - Bloomington, Ind, 1954 November 2
    - Louisville, Ky, 1954 November 3
    - Lexington, Ky, 1954 November 4
      Correspondence includes arrangements and expenses for lecture tours; copy of presentations; announcement of tour #72 lecture with biographical sketch and summary of talk.
  - Phila. Pa. Temple University lecture, 1954 April 7 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    Paper delivered "Exploration of chemical architecture".
  - Bklyn., NY Brooklyn Polytechnic Inst. symposium "current peptide and protein research", 1955 January 15 (Box 33, Folder 12)
    Paper delivered "Studies on peptides and proteins with countercurrent distribution methods".
  - Madison, Wisc. University of Wisc. Oscar Rennebohm lectures, 1955 May 16-18 (Box 33, Folder 13)
    Presentations:.
    "The use of extraction in studies with natural products".
    "The structure of the known naturally occurring peptides".
  - Phila., Pa. Rohm and Haas lecture, 1956 November 15 (Box 33, Folder 14)
    Paper delivered "Title? ".
  - Paris, XVI International congress of pure and applied chemistry. Dr. Craig NAS-NRC representative. No evidence of paper presentation, 1957 July 16-25 (Box 33, Folder 15)
    Copy of report to Sec'y of State from U.S. delegation.
  - Baltimore, Md. Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions Abel centennial meeting of the American Society for pharmacology and experimental therapeutics, 1957 September 4-7; Description of program: Typescript with corrections. (Box 33, Folder 16)
    John J. Abel centennial symposium. Paper delivered "The chemistry of insulin". Presentation and program.
  - NY City ACS series of lectures on "The identification and determination of structure of chemical compounds", 1958 February-April (Box 33, Folder 17)
    Correspondence, program, handwritten outline of presentation and Craig et al published paper.
    Paper delivered September 5: "Criteria of homogeneity and methods of purification"
  - Pittsburgh, Pa. The Pittsburgh conference on analytical chemistry and applied spectroscopy, 1958 March 3-7 (Box 33, Folder 18)
    Program.
    Paper delivered March 3: "The present status of countercurrent distribution".
  - Month (?) Cleveland, Ohio ACS meeting Paper delivered "Some comparative structural and biochemical features of polypeptide antibiotics", 1960 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    Correspondence; working copy of presentation; abstract; handwritten slide outline.
  - NY City, NY Academy of Sciences conference on amino acids, peptides, and proteins, 1960 February 25-26 (Box 33, Folder 20)
    Paper delivered "Homogeneity studies with insulin and related substances".
    Correspondence; abstract of presentation and photocopy of pages 144-145 from I.H. Page "Chemistry of the brain" with reference to Craig and Jacobs.
  - NY City RU seminar on biochemical methods, 1960 April 27 (Box 33, Folder 21)
    Paper delivered "Countercurrent distribution".
    Typescript of presentation.
  - Chicago, Ill. Gas chromatography symposium, 1960 July 11-23 (Box 33, Folder 22)
    Correspondence; list of participants; outline of "Partition chromatography" (outline of possible Craig presentation) with working material.
  - Boston, Mass. Hemoglobin structure workshop, 1960 December 14-16 (Box 33, Folder 23)
    General workshop information; tentative program; copy of Craig presentation with corrections; copies of nomenclature proposal "Recommendations for the nomenclature of hemoglobins" originated at this Hemoglobin structure workshop.
    Craig presentation December 15: "on hemoglobin"
  - Location (?) ACS meeting, 1961 October 13 (Box 33, Folder 24)
    Paper delivered "The organic chemistry of proteins".
    Incomplete copy of presentation and handwritten slide outline.
  - NY City RU Christmas Lectures "On separating things", 1961 December (Box 33, Folder 25)
    - Lecture I: Wm. H. Stein. Introduction. Possible title "The large and the small"
    - Lecture II: L.C. Craig "Extraction"
    - Lecture III: L.C. Craig "Distillation"
    - Lecture IV: W.H. Stein "Crystals and ions"
    - Lecture V: S. Moore "Chromatography"
    - Correspondence; introduction with lecture outline; copies of presentations by 3 lecturers; Craig slide outline; photocopies of analysis and excerpts from questionnaire sent to all receiving tickets to Christmas lectures by C.I, Campbell
  - Boston, Mass. MIT. Holiday Science Lectures "On separating things" Lecturers: Wm. Stein, L.C. Craig and S. Moore, 1962 December 26-29 (Box 33, Folder 26)
    Correspondence; program; Craig biographical sketch; copies of Craig presentation and abstract.
  - Location (?) ACS meeting, 1963 (Box 33, Folder 27)
    Paper delivered "Diffusion through cellophane membranes".
    Abstract of presentation.
  - Buffalo, NY American Institute of Chemical Engineers (AIChE), 1963 May 5-8 (Box 33, Folder 28)
    May 6 Dr. Craig chairs symposium on membrane transport processes and delivers paper "Parameters involved in the separation of biological solutes by dialysis or ultrafiltration".
    Correspondence; program; typescripts of presentation and abstract; photocopies of abstracts by other symposium participants; reprints by Bixler et al.
  - New Brunswick, N.J. Rutgers University N.J. Science Teachers Assoc. meeting, 1964 April 25 (Box 33, Folder 29)
    Paper delivered "Separating things".
    Correspondence; program and typescript with corrections of presentation.
  - Upton, NY Brookhaven Nat'l Laboratory symposium on structure and function of polypeptide hormones: insulin, 1965 November 8-10 (Box 33, Folder 30)
    November 10: Dr. Craig chairs session on "Structure-activity relations of insulin and other peptide hormones"
    Correspondence; program; list of participants; handwritten notes.
  - University Park, Pa. Pennsylvania State University Chemistry Department colloquium, 1967 March 16 (Box 33, Folder 31)
    Paper delivered "The study of molecular shape and association phenomenon by membrane diffusion".
    Correspondence; programs (1965-66 and 1966-67); expenses.
  - Cleveland, Ohio Pittsburgh conference on analytical chemistry and applied spectroscopy, 1968 March 3-8 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    Correspondence; program; abstract of presentation "A rapid countercurrent dialyzer with analytical significance"' airline voucher.
    Paper delivered March 6 at Fisher awardee's symposium "Quantitative dialysis".
  - NY City Ru seminar on biochemical methods, 1968 October 9 (Box 33, Folder 33)
    Copy of what appears to be presentation and advance notes.
  - Bloomington, Ind. Indiana University chemistry colloquium, 1971 January 8 (Box 33, Folder 34)
    Paper delivered "Stereochemistry of complex polypeptides".
    Correspondence and preliminary program.
  - Brussels, Belgium Free University of Brussels seminar, 1971 September 24 (Box 33, Folder 35)
    Paper delivered "Conformational studies with polypeptides".
    Correspondence and mss by DeCaen et al.
  - Cologne, Germany Institut fr physiologische chemie der Universitt Kln seminar, 1971 September 27 (Box 33, Folder 36)
    Paper delivered "Conformation studies with polypeptides".
  - Gordon Research Conferences (GRC), 1952-1973; 3 boxes and 13 folders (Box 34, Box 35, Box 36)
    December 1953: Became member of advisory board of GRC; also member of GRC council (not clear when became member).
    1957: became member of GRC Bd. of trustees.
    1962: became member of GRC selection and scheduling committee (in 1966 Chairman).
    Dr. Craig actively involved in policy making and governing board of GRC. Includes correspondence as a working member of GRC: Advisory Bd., Bd. of Trustees, Council, Selection and Scheduling Committee (in 1966 Dr. Craig chairman of S & S Committee) and chairman of 1958 June GRC on separation and purification. Attends many meetings and presents papers at some.
    Also includes duplicated material: announcements of various committee meetings and conferences; various membership lists; agendas and minutes of various meetings; conference programs and lists of participants; and also includes newspaper, magazine, and journal articles on publicity about GRC and 1961-1966 W. George Parks photocopied and carbon copies of correspondence received from others for use as a working member of GRC Selection and Scheduling Committee:.
    Papers delivered at various GRC:.
    - Papers delivered
      Records are arranged chronologically within boxes 36-36.
      - GRC on "Separation and purification" Paper delivered "Countercurrent distribution" (No dates or location of conference), 1952
      - New Hampton, NH GRC on proteins and nucleic acids, 1953 August 24-27
        Paper delivered "Fractionation and isolation of peptides".
      - New London, NH GRC on separation and purification, 1956 June 25-29
        Paper delivered "Fractional dialysis and its relation to other separation techniques".
      - GRC on separation and purification, 1958 June 16-20
        Dr. Craig chairs this conference. Includes correspondence as working chairman.
      - New Hampton, NH GRC on proteins and nucleic acid, 1959 June 29-July 3
        Paper delivered "Membrane diffusion; separations based on size".
      - New Hampton, NH GRC on proteins, 1961 June 26-30
        P.M. session on fractionation of peptide mixtures.
        Paper delivered "Separation and characterization of peptides by membrane diffusion".
      - New London, NH GRC on separation and purification, 1961 August 7-11
        Includes summary of presentation.
        Paper delivered "Membrane diffusion".
      - New London, NH GRC on separation and purification, 1965 August 23-27
        Paper delivered "Differential dialysis".
      - New Hampton, NH GRC on proteins, 1967 June 25-30
        P.M. Dr. Craig chairs session on "Comparative amino acid sequence" and on June 30 A.M. participates in discussion on session on "Ultrafast reactions and H-D exchange reactions".
      - New London, NH GRC on separation and purification, 1968 August 19-23
        Paper delivered "Basic parameters of selective separations in biology". Includes abstract of presentation.
      - New London, NH GRC on separation and purification, 1972 August 21-25
        Paper delivered "Solution parameters involved in separations by partition'. ' Includes abstract of presentation.
    - 1952-1955 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - 1956-1957 November (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - 1957 December-1958 March (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - 1958 April-1958 July (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - 1958 September-1959 November (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - 1962-1962 August (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - 1962 August-1963 June (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - 1963 July-1963 December (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - 1964 January-1965 April (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - 1965 May-1965 December (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - 1966 January-1966 March (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - 1966 September-1973 (Box 36, Folder 4)
- Laboratory data, 1945-1973; 7
  Primarily measurements (lab readings). Some by investigators in Craig laboratory. Includes some photographic prints and figures. Indications are used in mss publications and possible presentations. [Identified where possible]. Pages hand numbered consecutively.
  Arranged in approximate chronological order.
  - Examinations of metabolic products and QB-phenolic with some measurements by L. Goldman, 1945 1946; pp 1-25 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - L.C. Craig notebooks. (Spiral removed). Analyses of amino acids, polypeptides and antibiotics, 1948 1949; 2 items, pp 1-128 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - J.D. Gregory Outline of tyrothricin work and 1948 (?) June 20-July 1 handwritten report on bacitracin experiments, circa l948 1950; pp 1-13 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - L.C. Craig black notebooks. Analyses and experiments of amino acids and polypeptide antibiotic, 1950 March-1953 December; 2 items, pp 1-125 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Analytical data for amino acid isolated, 1949 1950 1952; pp 1-15 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Bacitracin A (amino acid analyses) [Internal evidence indicates may have been work for ms #137 in Craig bibliography], 1954 October; pp 1-45 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Membrane testing, 1956 April-July; pp 1-50 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Membrane testing for dialysis, circa 1958 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    Includes research report (typescript) pp 1-38.
  - S.P. Marfey Bacitracin - amino acid analyses, 1959 June 24; pp 1-92 (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Figures and tables used in published mss and possible presentation, 1960 March 1960 November (Box 37, Folder 10)
    Some photographs. Identified when possible pp 1-13.
  - Parathyroid hormone, 1959 1960 1961 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    Includes some photographs and illustrations pp 1-32.
  - CCD-DNP-Valine, 1960 November 1961 May (Box 37, Folder 12)
    Includes some photographs and slide outline for possible presentation pp 0-24.
  - Oxytocin data, 1961 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    Includes 1963 letter from V. du Vigneaud with biological potencies of oxytocin and various analogues on Craig samplespp 1-24.
  - Polypeptide and amino acids (original folder indicates instructions for illustrations), 1963 April 2; pp 1-5 (Box 37, Folder 14)
  - Bovine growth hormonepp 1-12, 1964 December 1965 January-March 1965 June (Box 37, Folder 15)
  - Chymotrypsinpp 1-11, 1965 March (Box 37, Folder 16)
  - Chymotrypsinogen and chymotrypsin - salt effect, 1965 April-July; pp 1-62 (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - Lysozyme - salt effect, 1965 May-July; pp 1-29 (Box 37, Folder 18)
  - Lysozyme-pH and NAG studies, 1965 July-September 1965 November-December; pp 1-36 (Box 37, Folder 19)
  - Dialysis-Ribonuclease salt effect and pH study, 1965 August-December; pp 1-53 (Box 37, Folder 20)
  - Experimental dialysis tubing, 1966 March-May; pp 1-46 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Dialysis lysozyme, 1967 January 1967 June 1967 July; pp 1-34 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Rimon and Williams reports, 1965-1967 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    Includes 1965-1967 list of publications of Weizmann Institute, Rehovoth, Israel. 1967 May 25 Williams, R.C. report on "Observations of the dialysis of nonideal solutes" with measurements [nd] Rimon report on experiments on IgM degradation with measurements. pp 1-26.
  - Lysozymes, 1967 September-November 1968 January; pp 0-29 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Lysozyme activity, 1968 January-March; pp 1-129 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Chen Collagen membrane - t 1/2 lysozyme and insulin, 1966 May-June 1968 November; pp 1-11 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Tyrocine, 1968 January-February 1968 April (Box 38, Folder 7)
    Includes some lab readings by N.J. Leonard. pp 1-39.
  - (?) Harry Chen Data and various original diagrams, 1969; pp 1-13 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Equilibration of NAG by CC dialysis, 1969 March 1969 October; pp 1-18 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - H.C. Chen Lysozymes, 1969 March (Box 38, Folder 10)
    Includes figures by illustrations dept. pp 0-25.
  - NAG binding to lysozyme, 1969 January 1970 May (Box 38, Folder 11)
    Includes handwritten outline for possible ms. pp 1-36.
  - 1969 February-March 1969 June-July (Box 38, Folder 12)
    Includes "Thin film dialysis of deoxyribo-oligonucleotides" ms (photocopy with corrections - Heimer; Nussbaum handwritten names on ms) pp 1-46.
  - Membrane modification, 1970 September-November 1971 January-February; pp 0-65 (Box 38, Folder 13)
  - Dr. Chen Lysozyme mM Primarily figures by illustrations dept, 1970 June; pp 0-16 (Box 38, Folder 14)
  - Adenosine, cylidin, uridine, bacitracin, ferrichrome, 1971 January-February; pp 1-30 (Box 38, Folder 15)
  - Dialysis SDS (Dr. Chen) and ninhydrin analysis (by Valerie Dalin), 1971 April-June; pp 1-33 (Box 38, Folder 16)
  - DPG experiments - dialysis (membrane 18g3) H. Chen, 1971 June; pp 1-30 (Box 38, Folder 17)
  - Beaker dialyzer testing; dialysis behaviour, 1971 February 1969 (Box 38, Folder 18)
    1971 Feb. correspondence indicates Craig evaluation of Dow Chemical "beaker dialyzer". Also includes 1969 measurements of dialysis behaviour of various solutes. pp 1-42.
  - Viscosity effect on dialysis, 1971 December; pp 0-5 (Box 38, Folder 19)
  - TNS fluorescence Primarily measurements, 1971 May-December 1972 February (Box 39, Folder 1)
    Includes some correspondence, reprints by others and figures for //257 in Craig bibliography from illustrations dept. pp 0-168.
  - Binding studies by countercurrent dialysis, 1972 May; pp 1-2 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Dialysis tubing testing, 1972 September-November (Box 39, Folder 3)
    Includes photocopy of P.F. Cranefield/j.W. Burnett correspondence re: collaboration on toxin problem. pp 1-8.
  - Michael J. Harris Linear peptides, 1972 1973 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    Includes reprints by others and 3 handwritten M.J. Harris mss:.
    - 1) "The thin-film dialysis of hexapeptides Part I"
    - 2) "The thin-film dialysis of hexapeptides Part I"
    - 3) "Synthesis and dialysis of peptides-a summary" with corrections, 1972 July 28; pp 1-62
- Laboratory data, 8
  Includes correspondence re: sample testing; analyses. Also includes charts; graphs; measurements; some notes; literature and reports. Some by investigators in Craig laboratory. Pages hand numbered consecutively as found.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Angiotensin II Dialysis of, 1961-1963; pp 1-48 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Bacitracin, 1954 1955 1957 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    Correspondence; notes; chromatograms; graphs. pp 1-76.
  - Bacitracin, 1962-1963 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    T. Schleich lab work and research notes. pp 1-38.
  - Bacitracin, 1963-1964 1967-1968 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    Correspondence includes Dr. Craig 1963 Apr. 11 "Analysis of the proposed second international standard for bacitracin" and charts; graphs; measurements; also 58 page photocopied 1963 (?) ms "A collection of research reports on the chemistry of the peptide bacitracin". pp 0-104.
  - Bacitracin, 1967-1968 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    Includes binding studies of bacitracin and 1 item correspondence.
  - Bacitracin, 1969-1971 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    Correspondence includes: Lectures: 1970 Jan. 22-23 Peoria, I11. Northern Regional Laboratory (NRRL) Series 7 lecture program.
    Lectures delivered by Dr. Craig: Jan. 22 A.M. "Types and applications of semipermeable membranes used for dialysis and filtration" and P.M. "Theory and application of reverse osmosis and differential dialysis".
    "Significance in related areas and new developments". pp 0-22.
  - Binding, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    Includes 1973 Jan. 22-23 N.Y. Academy of Sciences, conference on drug protein binding abstracts. T.P. King: in Craig laboratory presents paper (Abstract #7) and 2 items correspondence on binding investigative work. pp 1-5.
  - Chromatography, 1962 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    Photocopy of advance notes of E.H. Ahrens 1962 May 23 RU seminar "Gas liquid chromatography" and 1962 Brinkmann bibliography on "Thin layer chromatography". pp 1-5.
  - Dialysis, 1963-1973 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    Correspondence includes literature; also experiments with measurements. pp 1-58.
  - Edeine (G. Roncari), 1962 1963 1965 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    Correspondence; partial ms.; amino acid analyses; lab notes and data. pp 1-91.
  - Edeine, 1967-1969 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    Correspondence includes literature. pp 1-8.
  - Gel filtration, 1964 1973 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    Correspondence; literature. pp 1-27.
  - Gramicidin, 1949 1950 1959 1962 1964 1965 1966 1967 1968 1970 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    Correspondence; reports on collaborative work.
    Literature; analytical data; lab notes and measurements. pp 0-99.
  - Hemoglobin, 1960 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    Correspondence; photocopied lab notes and measurements. pp 1-19.
  - Insulin, 1953 1954 1955 1956 1957 1959 1960 (Box 41, Folder 4)